Guide to the Bertram Borden Boltwood Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bertram Borden Boltwood papers
1890-1932
MS 90
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(8 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, laboratory notebooks, lectures, and other writings of B.B. Boltwood, scientist and professor of radiochemistry at Yale, best known for his early work in the study of radiation. Of particular note is Boltwood's extended correspondence with Lord Rutherford, the father of atomic physics.
Boltwood, Bertram Borden, 1870-1927
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Subject File.
Scope and Contents
Bertram Borden Boltwood (1870-1927) is best known for his work in the field of radioactivity. Important contributions by Boltwood in this field include: the discovery of a new chemical element, ionium; the proof that uranium, ionium, and radium are genetically related; the proof that certain elements could not be chemically separated which led to the discovery of isotopes by Frederick Soddy and Kasimir Fajans; the proof that lead is the end product of the uranium-radium series; the development of the method used to determine the age of the earth, based on the ratio of lead to uranium; and the proof that actinium is a genetic descendant of uranium in a different line than radium. Much of Boltwood's work in radioactivity seems to have been inspired by suggestions made by Ernest Rutherford (Lord Rutherford), the father of atomic physics. In turn, Boltwood's proofs of various radioactive theories supported Rutherford's findings and provided a basis for further discoveries. The Boltwood-Rutherford correspondence, consisting of approximately 125 letters dating from 1904 to 1924, forms an important part of these papers.
Correspondence and writings make up the bulk of the Bertram Borden Boltwood Papers. Besides the correspondence with Lord Rutherford, there is, correspondence with other notable scientific figures including: Frederick Soddy, pioneer in the field of isotopes; Otto Hahn, discoverer of nuclear fission; Stefan Meyer, physicist and director of the Radium Institute in Vienna; Ellen Gleditsch, Norwegian chemist who, under Boltwood's direction, determined an accurate method for determining the half-life of radium; Howard A. Kelly, pioneer in the application of radium to malignancies; and physicists Hans Geiger, Robert W. Wood, A. S. Eve and J. C. McLennan. Boltwood's correspondence also includes letters of advice as chemical consultant to miners, prospectors and chemical manufacturers.
The writings of Bertram Borden Boltwood include laboratory notebooks which cover the years 1892-1893, 1896-1900, 1904-1917, 1924, and 1926. There are also drafts of lectures on radioactivity, as well as several copies of scientific reports stemming from Boltwood's work as a consulting chemist. Four drafts of scientific papers attributed to Boltwood are found in the papers. They deal generally with the disintegration products of uranium.
The section on writings of others includes four papers by Lord Rutherford and "The Life of Radium" by Ellen Gleditsch.
See: Rutherford and Boltwood: Letters on Radioactivity. Edited by Lawrence Badash. Yale University Press, 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Bertram Borden Boltwood (1870-1927), born in Amherst, Massachusetts, was the son of Thomas Kast Boltwood (1844-1872) and Margaret Mathilda Van Hoesen (1842-1909), and the grandson of Lucius Boltwood (1792-1872) and Fanny Haskins Shepard (d. 1888).
Boltwood attended Albany Academy, Albany, New York, before entering Sheffield Scientific School of Yale University in 1889. He graduated from Sheffield in 1892 with the highest rank in chemistry. From 1892 to 1894 Boltwood studied rare earths and analytical methods in Germany. Boltwood returned to Yale as an assistant in chemistry in 1894 and was made an instructor of chemistry in 1896. He received his Ph.D. degree in chemistry from Yale in 1897. In 1900 Boltwood left Yale to open a private laboratory in New Haven which he operated with mining engineer Joseph Hyde Pratt until 1906. It was during this latter period that Boltwood began his career as a consulting chemist to manufacturers, miners, and prospectors.
Boltwood became interested in the field of radioactivity around the time Rutherford and Soddy announced their theory of disintegration of radioactive elements in 1900. Stimulated by the prospect of a visit by Rutherford to New Haven in 1904, Boltwood began experiments to prove that uranium and radium exist in a constant ratio in unaltered minerals. The results of the experiments gave strong support to the disintegration theory. Impressed with Boltwood's work, Rutherford urged him to continue working in the field. Rutherford's visit to Boltwood's laboratory in New Haven marked the beginning of a productive, friendly association between the two men. Boltwood's successive experiments in radioactivity led to the important discoveries and proofs referred to in the preceding pages.
Boltwood returned to Yale in 1906 as assistant professor of physics. During the academic year 1909-1910 Boltwood worked in Rutherford's laboratory at the University of Manchester. Upon his return from abroad, Boltwood was made professor of radiochemistry of Yale College, a position he held until his death in 1927. By this time, however, Boltwood's years of productivity in the field of radioactivity were largely over.
In the years following his return from England, Boltwood assisted Professor H. A. Bumstead in the building of the Sloane Physics Laboratory (1912) and became its acting director during Bumstead's absence in 1913-1914. Boltwood later devoted much of his time to planning the construction and equipment of the Sterling Chemical Laboratory (1921). This work seems to have put a tremendous strain on Boltwood's health and he suffered several nervous breakdowns before his eventual suicide in Maine on August 15, 1927.
Additional biographical material may be found in the Dictionary of American Biography, in A. S. Eve's biography, Rutherford, and in Rutherford and Boltwood, Letters on Radioactivity, edited by Lawrence Badash.
Nuclear physics; Radioactivity; Science; Educators; Physicists; Boltwood, Bertram Borden, 1870-1927; Rutherford, Ernest, 1871-1937; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
- Correspondence, 1890-1928; Series I; 15" - 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by name of writer or recipient in two sections: General Correspondence and Correspondence of Others. Selected correspondence is filed in folders bearing the name of the correspondent. The remaining correspondence is arranged under the appropriate letter of the alphabet.
  General Correspondence is about evenly divided between correspondence with other scientists and correspondence revolving around Boltwood's career as a chemical consultant for manufacturers, miners, prospectors, and the United States Government.
  The correspondence with other scientists is especially valuable in studying the development of theories and the growth of knowledge about radioactivity and the atom. In addition to the correspondence with the notable scientific figures already mentioned, the correspondence between Boltwood and Lord Rutherford, the father of atomic physics, which consists of approximately 125 letter written between 1904 and 1924, is of special interest.
  As a consulting chemist, Boltwood corresponded with representatives of government agencies such as the Department of Agriculture and the Bureau of Standards, with representatives of large companies such as the Standard Chemical Company, Pittsburgh, and the German Gold and Uranium Mining Company, Denver, as well as with industrialists, notably A. I. DuPont. This correspondence throws light on the growth of the technology of radioactive materials.
  Also included under General Correspondence are fourteen letters written by Boltwood to his mother from Europe during the summer of 1890.
  Correspondence of Others is a very small section containing only seven letters. This includes two letters written by Rutherford to Lansing Hammond, Boltwood's heir, after Boltwood's death and one letter from Rutherford to H. A. Bumstead dated 1908.
  - General Correspondence
    - A., 1911, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alsberg, C. N., Chief of Bureau of Chemistry, USDA, 1914, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Angell, James Rowland, President of Yale University, 1921, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - B., 1907, 1911, 1913-1915, 1918, 1920-1923, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Baskerville, Charles, Professor of Chemistry at CCNY, 1910-1911, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Baumbach, Otto, 1910, 1915, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Becker, George F., 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Blan, S. A., 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bleecker, Warren F., 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Boltwood, Bertram Borden: letters to his mother, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Boltwood, Bertram Borden: letters filed under correspondent (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bosworth, Rowland S., 1911-1913, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Boyd, Thomas W., 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Boyle, R. W., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Brill, Otto, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Browne, Hugh C., 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bumstead, Henry Andrews, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Burnam, Curtis F., M. D., 1911-1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - C., 1911-1918, 1920, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cattell, James McKeen, 1910, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Chininfabrik Braunschweig, Buchler & Co., 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Collins, W. D., Food Investigation Chemist, USDA, 1914, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Craig, Archibald Gordon, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Craig, William Jr., 1916, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Curran, Thomas F. V., 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - D., 1910-1911, 1913-1915, 1919, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Dana, Professor E. S., 1910-1911, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Day, George Parmly, Treasurer of Yale, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Deaderick, William H., 1913-1914, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Denison, W. C., 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Dorsey, N. Ernest, Bureaus of Standards, 1913-1915, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - DuPont, Alfred I., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      General
      See also: box 7, folder 49
    - Dwight, Mrs. Timothy, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dwight, Winthrop E., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - E., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Eve, A. S., 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - F., 1910-1911, 1919, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Fleck, Alexander, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Foote, W. M., Foote Mineral Co., 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Fowler, Eileen Rutherford, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - G., 1911, 1913, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Geiger, Hans, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Giesel, F., 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Gleditsch, Ellen, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - H., 1906, 1910, 1914, 1919, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Hadley, Arthur T., President of Yale Univ., 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Hahn, Otto, 1906-1907, 1910-1911, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Hooper, Franklin W., The Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Hopkinson, Sir Alfred, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - J., 1918, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Johnstone, J. H., 1919, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - K., 1910-1911, 1914, 1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Kamerlingh-Onnes, Dr. H., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Kelly, Howard A., M. D., 1911, 1913-1914, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - L., 1910-1911, 1913-1915, 1919, 1924, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Leavitt, C. W., and Co., 1911 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Ledoux & Company, 1910, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Lees, George E., Standard Chemical Co., 1911 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      See also:
      Joseph M. Flannery, box 1, folder 37
      Otto Brill, box 1, folder 15
      Charles H. Viol, box 3, folder 94
    - Lieber, Hugo, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Lockwood, Stephen T., 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Lyman, Theodore, 1911, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - M., 1910-1911, 1913-1914, 1920, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - McLaren, George, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - McLennan, J. C., 1914, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - MacMillan & Co. Ltd., 1910-1911, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Menge, G. A., USDA, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Meyer, Anna, 1916, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Meyer, Stefan, 1911, 1913-1915, 1920, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Meyer, Stefan, Secretary of the International Radium Standards Committee, 1910-1912, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Miner, H. S., 1907-1909, 1911, 1914, 1919, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Moore, R. B., 1911, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - N., 1913, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Nesmith, Loring Gale, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - O., 1896, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - P., 1913, 1920-1921, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Paddock, H. C., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Parsons, Charles L., Secretary of the American Chemical Societ, 1910, 1914-1915, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Pegram, George B., 1910-1911, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Pickett, George B., 1914 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Puckner, W. A., American Medical Assoc., Council on Pharmacy and Chemistry, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - R., 1911, 1913-1914, 1919, 1921, 1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Radium Limited, USA, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Richards, Professor T. W., Harvard, 1913-1914, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Lord Rutherford, 1904-1905 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Lord Rutherford, 1906-1916, 1919-1922, 1924, undated (Box 3, Folder 85-88)
    - Rutherford, Mary, 1913, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - S., 1904, 1907, 1910-1916, 1918, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Soddy, Frederick, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Secretary of Yale University, 1910-1918 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - T., 1911-1912, 1920, 1922, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - U, V., 1914, 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Unidentified, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - van Arsdale, G. D., 1911-1912 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - W., 1911, 1913-1916, 1921-1922, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Wheelock, C. W., 1911 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Williams, Francis, M. D., 1914 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Wood, Henry E., 1911 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Wood, R. W., 1921 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - X, Y, Z., 1905 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - Claus, P., to Yale University, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Moore, Richard B., to Dr. Parsons, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Rogers, Henry T., to George Parmly Day, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Lord Rutherford to H. A. Bumstead, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Lord Rutherford to Lansing Hammond, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 107)
- Writings, 1890-1926; Series II; 1' 51/2" - 4 boxes
  WRITINGS are arranged in two sections: Writings and Writings of Others. The material in the first section is arranged alphabetically by type; material in the latter section is arranged alphabetically by author.
  The Writings of Bertram Borden Boltwood include laboratory notebooks covering the years 1892-1893, 1896-1900, 1904-1917, 1924, and 1926, a journal dated June 25-July 17, 1890, and undated notes for a series of lectures on radioactivity, all in Boltwood's hand. There are also type-written drafts of scientific reports, notably Boltwood's findings on the radioactive content of the waters around Hot Springs, Arkansas dated 1904, as well as some drafts of scientific papers concerning the disintegration products of uranium. Finally, there are a series of twelve ore analyses, an autobiographical sketch, and score miscellaneous scientific notes.
  The Writings of Others consist almost entirely of drafts or printed copies of scientific papers. There are four papers by Rutherford. Of particular interest is the draft of Ellen Gleditsch's "The Life of Radium," in which an accurate method for determining the half life of radium is presented.
  - Autobiographical Sketch, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book Review by BBB on Unit Photography by F. M. Steadman, June 1, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Journal, June 25-July 17, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Laboratory Notebook, 1892-1893, after 1898 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Laboratory Notebook, 1896, 1900, 1904-1911 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Laboratory Notebook, Circa 1896-1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Laboratory Notebook, Volume B, 1905, 1907-1908, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Laboratory Notebook Index, Vol. 1-8, 1906-1908 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Laboratory Notebooks, Vols. 1-4, January 1906-September 1907 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Laboratory Notebooks, Vols. 5-8, September 1907-November 1908 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Laboratory Notebook, after 1910?, circa 1908, after 1910?, 1909-1914, 1916, December 1913-July 1914, 1917, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 11-16)
  - Lecture: Elementary Chemistry, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Lecture: Radioactivity:
    - I. Discharge of Electricity through Gases, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - II. The Ion Properties of Radioactive Substances, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - III. Radiations and Occurrence of Radium, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - IV. Radioactive Change, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - V. The Rare Gases of the Atmosphere, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Lecture: Radioactivity and its Bearing on Chemical Theories (BBB?), undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Lecture Outline: Chemistry of Engineering Materials Review, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Memoranda on the chemical Situation, Dec 1917, December 1917-February 1918 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Memorandum: On the Occurrence of Uranium Ores, their Uses and their Commercial Value, with Special Reference to the Pitchblende Ore found in Gilpin County, Colorado, December 7, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Chemistry lectures, 1921, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Notes: Elementary Theoretical Chemistry, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Notes: Miscellaneous notes on radioactivity, 1921, 1925-1926, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Notes:"On the State in which Helium Exists in Minerals," by Morris W. Travers, article appeared in Nature, Jun 12, 1905, June 12, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Notes: Organic Chemistry, September 26, 1905-? (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Notes: Physics, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Ore Analysis:
    - 1. Calculation of Ratio of activities of Minerals to Uranium, 1906? (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - 2. Polonium and Actinium, 1906, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - 3. Eve's Uraninite and Radium Solution, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - 4. Standard RaBr2 Solution and Uraninite, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - 5. N. C. Uraninite once Ignited, Calculation of U:Ra Ratio, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - 6. Activity of Florium and Thorium Minerals, undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - 7. Uranium Oxide, Ignition of in O and H, Phosphate from?, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - 8. Uranium Nitrate Solution, Gas from, Radium in, July 8, 1904? (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - 9. Thorianite, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - 10. Radium: Uranium, Direct Determination of Ratio Act., undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - 11. North Carolina Uraninite, Ignited own Blast, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - 12. North Carolina Uraninite, Third Heating, 1906? (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Outline for Elementary Organic, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Outlines to Professor LeBlanc's lectures on Allgemeine und Physikalische Chemie, S.S. Leipzig, April 28, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Report: Criticism of Method of Treatment of Carnotite Ores as outlined in memorandum, 1911? (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Report: the Radioactive Properties of the Waters of the Hot Springs on the Hot Springs Reservation, Hot Springs, Arkansas, 1904 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Report: Radium Estimates, for Mr. DuPont, 1913? (Box 7, Folder 49)
    see also: box 1, folder 32 Corres. With Forbes Rickard
  - Scientific Paper: Atoms and Molecules, November 16, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Scientific Paper: The Life of Radium, undated (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Scientific Paper: notes made by BBB on an article in Journal of the American Chemical Society (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Scientific Paper: The Relative Activity of Radium and the Uranium with which it is in Radioactive Equilibrium, by BBB and J. H. L. Johnstone, undated (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Scientific Paper: The Ultimate Disintegration Products of Thorium as indicated by the pro-portions of Lead and Helium in minerals, November 14, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Writings of Others
    - Bishop, H. E.: "The Present Situation in the Radium Industry," Science, March 23, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Crommelin, C. A.: "Apparatus and methods in the Cryogenic Laboratory," reprinted from Transactions of the Faraday Society, No.53, Vol. XVIII, part 2, with notes by BBB, December 1922 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Gleditsch, Ellen: "The Life of Radium", undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Haywood, J. K.: "Analysis of the Hot Springs on Hot Springs Reservation and Geological Sketch of Hot Springs, Arkansas", 1902 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Jones, Lauder William: "Electromerism, A Case of Chemical Isomerism Resulting from a Difference in Distribution of Valence Electrons," Science, November 23, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Langley, Clifford: Thesis, June 1899 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Robb, Alfred A.: poem, "An Alpha Ray", undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Lord Rutherford (and BBB?): "Amount of Radium in Uranium?", undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Lord Rutherford and J. Chadwick: "The Bombardment of Elements by #-particles," reprinted from Nature., March 29, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Lord Rutherford: "Henry Gwyn Jeffreys Moseley," reprinted from Nature, September 9, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Lord Rutherford: "Radioactivity", undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
- Subject file, 1897-1932; Series III; 21/2" - 1 box
  The SUBJECT FILE contains a few anonymous articles concerning Yale University, some papers relating to Boltwood's position at Yale, a bibliography of radioactive salts, some biographical information on Boltwood, miscellaneous certificates, scientific tables and graphs, a grade book, newspaper clippings, photographs, publishers agreements, and papers concerning United States of America v. Mountain Valley Water Company. Entries are arranged alphabetically by subject matter.
  - Articles: The New Sterling Chemistry Laboratory of Yale University," (2), anonymous, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Articles for Yale Scientific Magazine, anonymous, 1930-1932 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography: radioactive salts, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Biographical sketches, 1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Birth certificate, 1870 July 27 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - BBB: appointment as acting professor of chemistry, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - BBB: eulogy, Yale University, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - reprint, Nature, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - BBB: resolution concerning his death; Chemistry Department, Yale University, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Book Review: Les Notions Fondamentales d'Element Chimique et d'Atom, by Georges Urbain, anonymous, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Certificates of attendance: Royal Bavarian Ludwig-Maximilian University of Munich; University of Leipzig, 1892; 1896 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Certificates of membership:
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1913 January 8 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1920 December 27 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1911 April 22 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      See: Folio
    - Chemische Gesellschaft, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - National Academy of Sciences., 1911 April 20 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Chemical tables in French., undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Chemistry course requirements: brief outlines by BBB, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)